Hi everybody.
Hello. Was it just lunch?
Yeah. Did you eat on campus or did you
leave?
There was free food. They ate here. Did
anybody venture out into the big city?
Yeah. Where'd you go?
Were they New York sandwiches? Yes. That
means like pastrami piled up or what?
Um, well, I'm a vegetarian, so it wasn't
that exciting. It just Okay. Okay.
Sorry. There's a terrific dumpling place
not far from here called Ali's. Okay.
Um, Colia students, I'm sure, can can
vouch for this. How was it? How was
Ali's? It was It was very good. It was
super good. It was great. Good. Did you
have the Do you have the dumplings?
That's what you got to have. I got the
the wantton soup and then my friend Maya
got the the dumplings. Dumplings. Oh,
awesome. Awesome. So, we got a thumbs up
on the dumplings. Did anyone go to my
favorite place, the Hungarian pastry
shop? Yeah. Heck yeah. It's it's it's
purum, right? They must have the
hamandashen. I like to get the poppy
seed myself. Do we have any prune fans
here? Poppy seed is the sort of classic
hamashen.
You like the prune hamashen? I like pun.
Oh yes, we all like
pun. So,
okay. So, you are here
for making good trouble with AI, guys.
Get ready. That's right. This is going
to be interactive. We're going to try
not to get on the stage, but we're going
to put one of you on stage. Um, so get
yourself ready. Uh, prepare yourself to
volunteer. But there will be candy.
There's one. Whoa. Candy.
We Yeah. No, we didn't realize we were
going right after lunch, but when we
found out, Ben went out and got candy.
uh to keep everybody alert. Uh fall
asleep at the next one. Coming in.
We're going.
You got to wait. It got to be a reward.
You got to earn it. You got to earn it.
Scott says you have to earn it. Scott,
who are you? I am Scott Klene. Uh for
many Oh, thank you. for many years. Uh I
worked at ProPublica uh here in New
York. Uh but I have since then left and
I now work uh I'm trying the world of
software out. So, uh, I now work at
Automatic. Uh, who here has heard of
WordPress. There we go. So, we are the
company that makes WordPress, but I work
on a team that, uh, works with many,
many small newsrooms around the country.
Um, so I'm sure that we have a a
publisher who uses Newspack, um, at the
city you guys live in, but we don't have
to get into that because we're not here
to talk about that. And who are you,
Ben? Hi, my name is Ben Welsh. I live
here in Manhattan with my wife, but I'm
a relatively new New Yorker. I've only
been here about two years. I work at
Reuters News in Times Square, but I'm
originally from Eastern Iowa. Do we have
any Ians in the house? What? Where?
Hell yeah. I grew up in Swisser. Right
there off 380. You know where it is.
Hell
yeah. And I am a nerd in the news. And I
don't know if Scott, do you
self-describe as a nerd? Do you identify
yourself? Abs self-describe others
describe me. I'm just sort of generally
it is a truism that I am a nerd. Yeah.
And so as you can probably tell from our
presentation which is about to begin
Scott and I are the nerds in the
newsroom, right? We are we have kind of
specialized roles that we've car carved
out over the last couple decades where
yes, we are reporters and yes, we are
editors, but we're also computer
programmers and product designers and
just tinkerers who are trying to help
the news industry kind of make it on the
new rough and tough digital frontier.
And but I just I will uh interestingly I
spent 25 years as the nerd in the
newsroom and now I'm the journalist in
the nerd room. Whoa. How's that? Uh, you
know, it's pretty awesome. I like it.
So, right. Um, all right. So, this is
going to be interactive. We're not going
to make people stand up, but we are
going to run at you with a microphone um
and ask you to kind of raise your hand
um and answer some questions. So, uh who
here is ready to play a game?
Ready or not, we're doing it. I don't
know why I asked. All right. Scott, call
on somebody. All right. Hold on. Hold
on. All right.
Sorry about that.
Uh, I got to be closer to do those
things, so I can't go that far. There we
go. Do you guys know this reference
anyway? No.
Hell yeah. War games. There you go. Here
comes your candy. We're going to play a
game of
word word association. Look it up. War
games was a movie from when I was a
young person. Uh, I gota Why do I keep
doing this? Word association. All
right, you ready?
Finally. Can we get there? All right.
So, what is the first thing the first
thing you think of when we say
scientist?
No, we raise hands. We're gonna We're
going to put you on mics. You again.
Nerd. Nerd. Wow, that's rough. How about
you? Biology. Biology. Very good.
Anybody else?
Oh, sorry. Smart. Smart. Andy, also
true. I like that.
Hold on. Wait. Good. Your answer.
Research. Awesome. Love it. Experiment.
Experiment. Fantastic. This is great.
These are Colombia kits. Yep. Big words.
Terrific. You earned some candy on that
one.
Ready? Should we move on to Ben? We We
have Yeah. What's the next word? These
are good. These are excellent.
Techie technologist technologist first
word that popped into your head. Yeah.
Computer. Computer. Computer.
You Zuckerberg. No. Weird. Zuckerberg.
Okay, I'll come over.
Um, Bay Area. Bay Area. Whoa. Bay Area.
It's true. Okay, we got some folks over
here. Scott, I'm making my way. All
right. Yes, you guys. Wait, we got some
candy. We got some candy earners over
here. Big mouse. Mouse. Okay. You know,
my intern last summer had never used a
mouse in her whole life. She was like,
"That's for old people." Did you guys
know that? Shocked me. You got a word?
Yes. This guy right here. Him. Great
word. The sequel to her.
What else we got for Techie? We need one
more. Okay. Yeah. How about you guy
right here, dude? One more. Another.
Wait. Okay. Wait. We got two more. Ben,
we got we got candy earners up here. Way
too much candy is what Scott's telling
me. Coding. Coding. Coding. That's a
good one. Perfect. Bro,
bro, I know plenty of Okay. of non bro
techies. All right. What's our next
word? Hold on, Ben. We didn't We are We
owe candy.
Yes. Okay, here you go. Like half of
this area. Just
don't selfidentify as candy earners. All
right. Engineer. You got a word?
Gears. Gears. Okay.
Robots. Not the first time. I sense
robot. Robots. I said gear. You're done.
Okay, you're out. Your cash machine.
Machine.
Building. Building. We got building for
engineer. I love it. Good. Robots.
Robots. More robots. Lots of robots.
school.
School you know where we are now.
Robotics. Robotics. More Rob. We got
robots. This is like a This is terrific.
All right. This is great. And we got one
more word, Scott. Or we got one more
word.
How do you say that one?
Okay. Okay. I was genuinely worried this
this is like a thing from my era and
didn't exist anymore. All right. All
right. These still exist, right? Good.
Olympiad. Olympiad. Okay, good. These
still exist. Thank you.
Derivative. Derivative.
Yeah, that had three syllables. Hell
yes. Mean Girls. Mean Girls. Wow.
Really? I didn't know. Does that happen
in Mean Girls? Is there a mathlete? The
new one or the old one? Oh, okay. Oh,
here we go. Another mathlete.
Competition. competition.
Okay. All right. Very good. Excellent.
Who uh who is owed a candy? I just want
to make sure we don't Did you get your
candy? You guys Oh, she don't want to
get She don't want candy. That's okay.
All right. Well, let us know there we
got way too much. So, you are all going
to get candy even if you didn't.
Science, techie, engineer, mathlete. We
did those four. All right. We got one
last one and we want you to dig deep and
just say what's the first thing that
comes to your head. Don't be afraid.
of my feelings. Ben can speak to him for
his own. All right. First word that came
into your head. Let's be honest. Yep.
Honest.
Writer. Writer. The first one we got was
writer. Okay. Interviewer. Interviewer.
Love it. Got one. These are all
terrific. Inquisitive. Inquisitive.
Excellent word. Such vocabularies.
Storyteller. Storyteller. Absolutely
love it.
Okay, I got one. I see one. I see one
over here.
Hero. Hero. Hell yeah. Yearbook.
Yearbook.
Yearbook. We got candy. Yep. Good. All
right. And let's get one right here,
Scott. All right. Oh, he's passing you
by.
Underpaid. I agree. That one is
absolutely true. Underpaid. That was
funny. One more reporter. My Yes,
reporter. Very good. Oh, here's your
candy.
Okay. I saw I heard a bit of a contrast
from the four before. Don't you think,
Scott? Yes. I I noticed that
immediately. The first four were very
similar, right? But journalists seemed
very different. So what the vibe I get
from the room is that you all think that
journalism is very different than
science, technology, engineering, and
math. Is that right? Is it sort of like
different? Like these like one of these
things doesn't That's definitely my era.
One of these things doesn't belong. Uh
yes. Okay. All
right. Well, we
think I'm not sure how to do this. Can
you do it? There you go. Come on, Scott.
You get some candy if you do it. Boom.
No. No. Not quite. Not yet. I got it.
You got it. I got it. It turns out
that's wrong. Sorry, you're wrong. That
is not true at
all. We think and we are we are proof
that science, technology, engineering,
and math are
all things that are useful in
journalism. and they are kinds of people
that journalists can be and kinds of
backgrounds um that journalists can
have. And we're going to talk a little
bit about some people that we know in
the news industry who come from science,
technology, engineering, ba math
backgrounds. Uh so this is a guy named
Peter Aldis. Do you want to talk about
Peter? Peter was a scientist and he got
bored and he thought working at the
bench and writing these papers that very
few people read wasn't a very good time.
and he decided to change it up and
become a reporter. And he took all the
skills that he developed as a scientist
and used those same skills to find and
tell stories, including stuff with AI,
which we can get into, and um in this
particular case, tracking uh government
spy planes and then writing about what
they're up to out there in the world.
Meanwhile, who can can anybody anybody
with really good vision can you read uh
what what Peter did in college?
He has his PhD in animal behavior. Um he
worked for a long time at BuzzFeed News
uh of Blessed Memory. Um and I'm not
sure where he is now, but you as Ben
says, he is an investigative reporter
that uses quantitative methods that he
learned studying animal behavior um to
do journalism projects. Um and as I
said, here's the the project on kind of
uh he figured out how to use uh
helicopter transponders. Every airplane
has a transponderant to sort of figure
out whether uh FBI, whether and why FBI
helicopters were uh were hovering over
places. So that's Peter Aldis, a
scientist. A scientist and a journalist
and a journalist. Not not one or the
other.
Scott, what's going on, dude? There we
go. Hell yeah.
Uh this is Jeff Cow. Uh Jeff uh works at
Bloomberg News now, though I worked with
him when he was at ProPublica. Um this
is a project that Jeff did uh in which
uh Bloomberg uh has a obviously who
knows about Bloomberg News? Who's heard
of Bloomberg News or the Bloomberg
terminal or Mayor Mike Bloomberg? All
sort of related to each other. Great. So
uh Bloomberg News Oh, I said I wasn't
going to go on the stage. Bloomberg News
uh did a project where they took uh so
who here's from New York
City? You are awesome. I'm also from New
York City. We um uh we just started this
thing called congestion pricing where
you pay a toll if you drive your car in
Manhattan under 60th Street. So you're
you're safe here, but if you drive your
car south of 60th Street, you get you
pay a toll. And critics of the program
said that uh this was not making traffic
any better. And Bloomberg wanted to see
if that was true. Um and
because we they have nerds,
uh Jeff and a band of his colleagues
aimed a high resolution camera out the
window of their building and then wrote
a computer vision piece of computer
vision software that counted the number
of cars that passed by. and they were
able to find out because they're they're
under 60th Street. Um they were able to
determine that thanks to congestion
pricing that actually the number of cars
in Manhattan did go down. Um and in fact
the computer vision they wrote was able
to determine the difference between a
civilian car, a cab, and other kind of
you know uh service vehicles. Um so this
was a program that they had to write to
kind of answer this question. Um and
where did Jeff go to school?
right here, right here, right on this
very campus. Um, he went to the
University of Wateroo in Canada where he
was
a he was an engineering major. Um, and
then, uh, he got a law degree here at
Colombia and then decided not to study
law, not to practice law. Um, but yeah,
so and Jeff um, so Jeff
is a techie. So, we have science and we
have
technology. Where are we gonna go
next? Ben, you want to talk about Arena?
Yes. So, Arena is a journalist who has
worked at NPR and um ProPublica and it's
now at the New York Times, I think, as
of a couple weeks ago. and she studied
actually engineering at Stanford
University and has since become a
journalist who like us works with data
to find and tell stories. Um, and
without those specialized skills,
without that nerdiness, she wouldn't be
able to do what she
does. That's right. These projects, so
they she did a project where she did not
just a whole lot of math to uh to do a
story about uh who here's from the
Pacific Northwest.
Oh, we got one. Yay. Uh, so there are,
uh, salmon fisheries. The salmon
industry in the Pacific Northwest has
really been, uh, you know, getting
smaller because of over damning, I guess
you would call it. Um, and so Inreina
did a big mathematical project to try to
figure out why that was happening and
whether the federal government's uh,
processes for fixing this were working.
Narrator, they're not. Uh, and so, uh, I
Ina used her quantitative skills and her
more traditional journalism skills,
whoever said interviewing and things
like that, to do this story, uh, working
with a reporter, um, out in Oregon. Um,
she also did a project, um, if you look
at the map, she did a project where she
looked to see, um, how many state
legislatures um, had fewer than 20 less
than 20% women. Um, and she found that
actually all of the ones apparently in
the
southeast, almost all the southeast had
legislatores that have less than 20%
women. So, uh, lots of math, lots of
engineering and and kind of technology
to be able to kind of find stories that
would otherwise not be findable. Keep
that in mind. We're going to be finding
stories in about a minute. Um, so Inrea
is actually probably both a scientist
and an engineer.
What does that leave?
And finally, we have Amanda Cox. Does
anyone know Amanda?
She is now the data editor at Bloomberg
News, where she runs a large team of
people, including the one Jeff's on, I
suppose, and has been a pioneer in uh
digital data journalism now for more
than 20 years or so, and did that after
studying statistics in college. That's
right. She got her bachelor's degree in
economics from St. Olaf. We have any any
St.
Olafs? Man, that would have been fun.
Uh, she got her bachelor's degree uh
from St. Olaf's and then she got in
economics and then got her master's
degree in statistics. So, what does that
make her?
There we go. She's our math. She's our
mathlete. And so, all of these people,
what do they all have in common?
They're nerds. Scott.
And
oh, oh, by the way, this is what this
is. Uh, do people know this? Amanda
invented the needle at the New York
Times election night. Yeah. Check it
out, guys. That's what that's needed.
Yeah. Yeah. We don't want to skip that
slide. That's That's Amanda's claim to
fame. They're all also journalists.
They're nerds and journalists. They're
are nerds and they're journalists. They
are not intention at all. um you can do
all of the things that a journalist does
and use your biology skills, your
engineering skills, your math skills.
You can bring all of yourself um to
journalists and we need all of that in
journalism and in newsrooms to tell the
stories that can be told now that have
to be told
now. So if we leave you with something
in addition to kind of showing you how
to use AI to do stuff, um it's that we
believe I believe Ben do you believe
this? With my full heart, Scott, I
believe with my full heart that
journalism is a STEM
major. Salaries haven't caught up
yet, but the reality is that we need
biologists and chemists and animal
behaviorists and electrical engineers um
and all of those things in
journalism. Um, which raises a
question, seeing everything that you've
seen and it's kind of thinking about the
words that you describe journalist
before we showed you all of those
slides. Knowing what you know now, what
is journalism?
Can someone define it for the class? Oh,
hell yeah. I love this. You're gonna get
if you answer. Break it down. I'm giving
you the mic. What's journalism?
Journalism is the ability to take a
story and distill it down into a
consumable format for the general
public. Okay. He's taking the production
angel, Scott. I kind of like that.
That's not bad. So, that was the
packaging and storytelling side. I love
it. I love it. Anyone else want to try
to define journalism? What's missing
from that definition?
Hand the mic. Let's hear this guy.
I think you might be trying to get at
the journalism side. That is the
scientific method. Maybe a little, but
there's the there's also the gathering
part is what I'm thinking. I heard the
publishing part. Yeah. You got to go get
that, right? Yeah. The gathering of
information. Yeah, man.
This is what we think journalism is. It
is all of those things as
well. But people are doing journalism
right now who don't call themselves
journalists, who don't realize they're
doing
journalism.
Journalism, it's a way of thinking. It's
a set of rules that keep us honest um
that hopefully make us credible in the
world. When we say something important,
people believe us because we apply we
impose rules upon ourselves. Um what are
the rules, Ben? What's a rule? Tell the
truth. Tell the truth. That's right.
Don't give money to political parties.
Yeah. Right. We sort of there's a little
bit of a monkishness to it about what we
can do and what we can't do. We don't
sign political uh pamph.
Yes. Uh we kind of hold ourselves out of
we don't go to protests, right? There's
some there are some rules to keep us
honest. We don't pay sources. Do people
know about that? Like if you ever hear
see a source, if you see a person
talking on TV, it is absolutely
forboden, forbidden to pay that person
for being on your air or for being for
stalking for your story there. So, it's
a set of rules that keep us honest, but
it's also a way of thinking. Um, and
it's already you've already seen it on
the board, so I don't have to go too
deeply into it, but one of those things
is um that we start with a question. Um,
we are all biased. We all have opinions.
Um, some of our opinions are really
deeply held. Some of those opinions are
political. Um, and we can't turn those
off no matter how many rules we make for
ourselves. But the important part is
that we start with a question, not an
answer. We don't we don't take an answer
and then find the proof that we need.
Um, the scientists you can call that uh
inductive, right? Inductive is when you
start with a answer and then and then uh
and then find the question. Um, we start
with the question um and find the
answer. And if we don't like where that
goes and if we if it goes against our
side or if it makes us feel really bad
and we wish it weren't true, it is too
bad. If if Ben if I was doing something
bad, which I'm not, and Ben figured it
out and wrote a story about me, even
though we're actually close friends, I
would understand. He would have to do
that,
right? And so to to return to our
examples, Peter started with the
question of what are all these we where
are the spy planes? Can I find them? I
know the government has them. Where are
they? How frequently do they fly? What
are they up to? Right. And then our
techie example, Jeff started with, is
congestion pricing actually reducing
traffic in Manhattan, which is what it
claims it's going to do? And Arena
started with the question of are we
approaching anything like gender parody
in our state legislatures, right? And
Amanda started with the question of can
we from the early election results as
they begin to emerge in the night give
you some sense of where they're going to
end up or a better sense of where
they're going to end up based on what we
know about the political science of it
all. So each of them started with a
question in a sense like any reporter
might but they used their science
technology engineering and math skills
to find the answers right and then even
some of those same skills to publish
something interesting on the internet as
well.
You can do it
Scott. Yeah. And in that way, but
journalism is not one thing. Journalism
is the intersection of things. Yes.
There's writing or photography or
illustration or coding, but it also is
an intersection with the what you bring
to it, the expertise that you have. My
whole career uh I have been a journalist
and an engineer. I have managed people
who are journalists and illustrators,
journalists and photographers.
Journalist and something is very much a
thing. Um, and frankly more so as
technology improves, as as the internet
happens, and as traditional newsrooms
are kind of competing with and working
with things like influencers and on
social media, um, and kind of building,
you know, helicopter trackers, um, stuff
that, you know, 40 years ago would not
have been a thing that news
did. There we go.
Um, really the most important thing. Can
I
swear? Ben, should I swear? You should
swear, Jennifer. Can I swear?
If you've never heard this before, tell
your parents. I'm sorry. But, uh, the
most important thing, the most important
skill of a journalist is giving enough
of a to use the stuff you're good
at to tell the truth. Should we give
Scott some candy for cursing? Oh, thank
you. Well done. Well done. That was not
easy for him.
Um,
so all right, I'm having one myself.
Okay. Is this the last candy question?
No, this is not the last candy question.
What is generative
AI? Only wrong answers. No, I'm joking.
You can give a right answer. It's like
you're putting in your ideas into it and
from what you put in it generates
something. Sure. Yeah. The generative.
Exactly. Generative generates. Exactly
right. You put in you put in some inputs
and it gives you some outputs. Anyone
else?
I got one here, Scott.
It's like uh kind of amalgamation of
code that uses a large data set of
information and then kind of recreates
it and replicates it in a unique and
original way. Pretty good, dude. That's
pretty good. Pretty good. That's
definitely worth the candy. What about
you? Can you top it? Top guy. Sorry,
Aaron. Um, I'd say something similar
like it's it has a lot of information
and it's instead of just like like a
regular search engine where it's just
pulling up an answer from something else
that already exists, it's going off of
other information and from that creating
something new. Pretty good. You got
something to add to that? We got one
more. One more. It uses statistics to
figure out what it's you're most likely
looking for and to use what the most
like most likely correct answer is based
on a massive set of data it already has.
Hell yeah. That was very good. Baze
himself would be proud. Here here's a
question. Now, I'm not talking about
your homework or essays or cheating in
any way because no one who gets
themselves invited to this conference
would ever do that. But who here has
used uh a conversational AI like chat
GPT or C-Pilot or
Gemini? Everybody love it. That's
fantastic to do what kind of stuff to
do. Again, you didn't do homework and
you're being recorded.
Uh what did you do? What did you use it
for? Um, when it first like came out, I
tried it out and I just like held a
conversation with it to see how useful
it was and how like responsive it was to
my questions. And was it was it
responsive to your questions? Yes.
That's awesome. That's great. Who else
who else is has an example of a time
they used genai for not homework and
you're being recorded? Yeah. Um, I wrote
a a program that uses chatbt to
automatically email professors and ask
for internships. That is awesome. Um,
and did it get you an internship? Um,
no. We only tested it on my mother and
she was not happy that we tested. Okay.
And she was already going to give you
the internship, so you didn't even need
to. Yeah. Yeah. So, all right. One more
and then we're going to start using
generative AI.
For art class, we were using generative
AI to try to compare to see if it would
replicate human art.
And did it? No. No. It was pretty bad.
Okay. One last one, Scott. All right.
Okay. Um, so for yearbook class, um, we
always have trouble like with headlines
and everything, so might as well just
ask AI to help us come up with a
headline for for like a page. How to do?
So, it did pretty good. Yeah. And it's
really nice, especially around like
final deadline time. Like I remember
like the final day like we were just
like we had like chat GPT up and we were
like typing like um aggressively to try
to find a headline and you know what it
worked. So that's awesome. That's great.
Um, so we're not going to get we only
have 15 minutes and we want to use a
genai so we're not going to go too
deeply into it but we've had some
excellent answers here somewhere in that
you're getting getting at the answer.
Um, who here but people have heard right
that there are some anxiety that Geni is
going to start taking jobs. I assume
everybody has heard that. Sure. Sure.
Um, I think very differently. I think
that generative AI is like the autopilot
of an airplane. I don't think that any
pilot jobs were lost when they
introduced autopilot. But flying got
safer. Um pilots started needing new
skills and they started using the
autopilot as much as flying the plane
themselves. So they still need to know
how to fly the plane themselves. And I
think it will be an incredible tool u
that will transform a lot of fields
especially journalism right and not just
in the English language stuff. We kind
of heard here we heard some English
class answers but also in those in the
STEM part of our work as well right in
the science technology engineering and
math side. So who said when we were
talking about journalism who said uh
interviewer? Awesome. That was a great
one. Thank you for that. I get extra
candy just extra credit.
So yes, interviewing is an incredibly
important part of of being a journalist
and you interview people. But one of the
sayings we have in data journalism is
interviewing the data. So the data just
like a person can also be interviewed.
Uh we also talk about how you trust it
exactly as much as you trust a person.
Uh which is not at all. Uh, but we are
going to use some AI to ask questions
about data uh to hopefully make some
good trouble. Um, who wants to be at the
Who has to type on my computer? Need to
volunteer. Red shirt. Do you want to
come do it? Awesome. Thank you. There's
like so much candy in this for you.
Yeah. Just don't look at the browser
history. Okay. No, no, no.
All right. What's your name? Uh, Enzo.
Enzo. Wonderful. Where are you from? Uh,
New York. Oh, from what part? Uh,
Harlem. You're from Oh, right around
here. Oh, that's awesome. That's great.
I am from
Brooklyn. Um, okay. So, you stand here.
No more slides. So, I'm like off the
hook now. Um, so who flew here? Who took
an airplane? Yeah. All right. Be
prepared to tell us the airport you flew
out of. This is going to be airplane
airport related information. Who here
knows what a what a runway incursion is?
A runway incursion, a government word,
if there ever was one. It's when there's
either a vehicle or like some sort of
fuel spilled on a runway or some some
reason why a plane can't land on a
runway. That is like three pieces of
candy right there. That is exactly
right. It is when something blows onto
the runway at a time when they don't
expect it to or something drives on the
runway or something is stuck on the
runway. Every time this happens, it
turns out that there's an FAA regulation
that says that the airport has to report
that to the federal government. This can
be trivial. It can be little nothing. It
could be uh you know, a person ran onto
it and was incredible dangerous. So, it
can be a lot of things. And the
government actually
publishes all of the data. So every
runway incursion in any airport in the
country uh is reported to the federal
government is actually put in this data
set um for uh a while. So let's So this
is it's been happening for a while. So
like 15 years I think. Um so I just need
an airport.
Wait, what's that? MSY. Oh MSY in uh in
in Minneapolis, right? Or New Orleans.
Sorry. All right. MSY. So, let's see
what we find from
MSY in New Orleans. Excellent. By the
way, airport code. Yes, airport code
knowledge is you're going to be a data
journalist. There we go. So, we can look
Louisiana MSY. And if you click on
search
RWRWS on the lower right, you can very
quickly see Oh, my session expired.
Hit okay.
Try it. Yeah. Yeah. Just do it again.
MSY. That's fine.
Right. There we go. So, we can see all
of the runway incursions that happened
at New Orleans uh airport um since a
while now, since 2017. And you can click
on each of these. Uh but Enzo, go back
to the page before.
How might we find out what airport in
the country has the most runway
incursions or who had the mo how many
are in runway incursions increasing or
decreasing? How would we figure that out
from this
interface? Uh I no candy there is no way
to figure that out in the interface.
That's something that you would have to
do like a data journalist like me or Ben
or like Ireina or Peter would download
the data or figure out how to get the
data from the government and run that
analysis themselves. But, and this is an
awesome trick that works with way too
many websites. If we uh if you actually
reload so that we don't have MSY in
anymore. Did that do it? Yep, it did.
So, if we put nothing in the search
form, try this. It works shockingly a
lot. Now, if you just with a blank
search, if you click on search
RWS, it will actually just give you all
the data. So, this is if you go to the
bottom, it'll tell you how many rows.
33,000 rows of data. So this I now have
we have as a as a group all 34,000
runway incursions that have happened in
United States since the teens. And if
you go to the
bottom you can see CSV download. So I
can take it and have it all to myself.
Three sweetest letters in the English
language. CSV. Anyone know what it
stands for? Hold on. Enzo knows. Enzo
sorry. Hell yeah, dude. Comma separated
values. Commaepparated values. And that
just means a spreadsheet. It's just like
a dumb acronym for means this is data in
a spreadsheet. Thank you. And so now we
can download it. And now should I Oh,
wait. What happened to my chat JPT? Oh
no. What' I do? I got this here. Hold on
one second. Hold that for me. Yeah.
Thanks. Now you're all seeing my uh my
browser history. Okay. Here we
go. So, this is chat GPT. People have
seen chat
GPT. So, with this uh this LLM with this
model, the 03 mini high is really good
at this, but you can actually use it
with a bunch of models. If you click on
plus on the left of that thing, you can
upload a file. So, upload from
computer. And I have already downloaded
the let me just go to the desktop.
I have already downloaded this. There we
go. So, here is the runway incursions.
And I'm going to hit open. Yeah. And
it's going to think about it a second.
And it's going to load all of this data
into its terrifying hive mind. Uh, and
it's going to be we're going to be able
to ask it's already there. So, now we
can interview the data. We can ask it
questions that are very interesting to
us. So, I'm going to start with one and
then I want to hear from others. Um, uh,
what airport has the most runway
incursions? Had the it'll figure it
out.
Reasoning considering airport runway
incursions. This this model is the
creepiest because it's going to tell you
how it's thinking about it. So, it asks
the user asked which runway incursion.
There's an uploaded file.
It's decided it has to load the pi the
file through some Python code. Let's try
that approach. What's Python code? Who
knows?
Anybody? Anybody know what Python is?
Enzo knows.
Yeah, it's I mean it's just like the
coding language that it's going to use
to try to interpret the data and like
list it all in into values. That's
right. It's a programming language and
you can use it to analyze data files.
And 10 years ago, you had to learn how
to write the code.
Now, Enzo is the perfect person to bring
up
here. Enzo, you are
awesome. Enzo, what has Chat GPD told
us? It's Chicago O'Hare Airport.
Um, anybody fly in from Chicago O'Hare?
You were just there. So, yeah. Careful
the runway incursions. I guess it's like
it is like a Titanic airport. Like I you
know, who knows, right? I I wouldn't
worry. Um and and Enzo just did this,
but if you actually click on the little
icon to the right, uh we can actually
see a little bit of the Python code that
it used uh to interpret this
information. And Ben, is that good
Python code? It's okay. It's just okay.
Better. Yeah. But it works, which hurts
me. And so you can imagine a reporter
who wants to interview the data can use
chat GPT for this. And if they have
enough Python, Enzo, do you think that's
good Python code? It's okay. It's fine.
It's fine. It's not like, you know,
we're not writing uh Microsoft Word or
something, right? It's, you know, it's
pretty simple. But um and so if you are
a programmer rather than writing all of
the code to do this yourself, you can
interview the data using check GPT
almost literally. But then you're a
programmer so you can look at the data
and understand like did it mess up? Like
did it do something that was wrong? Did
it do something that might lead to a
wrong answer. So who has other questions
that we would like to know about runway
incursions? We can ask and this is where
STEM hold on meets journalist runway
incursion. What is the most recent
runway incursion?
Okay, while it's thinking, let's put
yourself in the mind of a journalist and
tell me what you would do with the
knowledge that you gained by inter by
interviewing this data. Would you just
immediately write a story that said the
Chicago O'Hare has the most runway
incursions? You wouldn't, right? Why
not? It doesn't really like it's just
like it's an answer. It's not like a
story about like what's why does it have
the most? Excellent. Excellent. It's not
a story. It's just a fact. So, what
would you do to add add knowledge to
that so you could write it into a story?
What are the things that you might do?
Maybe interviewing someone who
experienced a runway encouragement at
Excellent. Excellent. Right. Sorry for
cutting you off. No. Right. interview
someone who has experienced a runway
incursion. What
else? Take
Well, first of all, sorry. First of all,
I would figure out what airport has the
most runway incursions per like amount
of flights. Hell yeah. Not just the most
amount. And then I would probably
explore that more than the first
question. Um, but I think like right
like going you like getting in contact
with people in the airport and figuring
out like what happens when there's a
runway incursion. What does that mean
for the plane and what um and why does
it happen and why is why is it happening
more in the one the airport that we're
looking at? Like what makes it
different? And especially for Chicago,
like if we're looking at per like
flights, like O'Hare is just a really
big airport. But like if we look at per
like flights, then what's the difference
between like O'Hare and Midway, right?
And like why? You're exactly right. You
know what I mean? I think normalizing by
a denominator for a rate is almost
always the right answer. Some airports
are bigger than others. A bigger airport
should have more incursions. Your
logic's right. I myself worked on a
story about helicopter accidents and we
we to the Robinson R44 helicopter
according to analysis of a similar
database had the most accidents but
guess what it's the most common
helicopter right and so we wanted to
calculate an accident rate before we
said it was the deadliest right so that
was uh crashes per flight hour in this
case it might be what incursions per
takeoff or something takeoff per landing
right you want it per something so that
you can tell is this a big deal or not?
In journalism, sometimes we say, "Is
this a man bites dog story or a dog
bites man story?" And if your editor
says to you, "This is a dog bites man
story," that means you're done. That's
it. Like, you're not allowed to publish
your story. Uh, it means it's not
newsworthy and not surprising. So, what
is Have you heard of that? Have you
heard the dog bites man versus man bite
dog? It makes sense. It's like an old
person thing to say. So, but still um
you will definitely hear it if you're an
industrial. Um all right, I think we
have time for one more query of the data
and then we be then we need to wrap up.
Uh Enzo, do you want to take typers
privilege?
Um sure. What's your question? Yeah, I
say it out loud. Let's think. Well, I
mean we can ask just ask the question of
how what is the airport that has the
highest density of incursions per
takeoff?
Let's ask. Absolutely. Let's do it.
Yeah. I don't think the data is in
there. This is where it's going to get
created. It might go for it, dude.
Right. What Ben is saying, one of the
things we didn't do when we asked the
first question is we didn't tell it to
limit its knowledge to what's in the
data. So, you're normally, and you're
writing a prompt like this, there's this
concept called prompt engineering where
you kind of know how to write these
prompt. And we normally would say, don't
go outside the data set to figure things
out. Um, and so, right, I think Ben is
right. I think if we put that in, it's
going to see if it can figure out how
many takeoffs every runway in the
country has.
But let's see if reasoning says that,
right? Clarifying airport incursion
data. While we wait, I mean, what's
truly incredible about this as I stuff
my face with chocolate is to do this
type of interviewing of a data set as a
journalist, you used to have to spend
weeks or months learning how to be a
computer programmer. And now these tools
are just making it much more accessible.
They are imperfect, but they're a great
start. We could try clicking search and
letting it use the internet. But but
what's important here is that it
actually identified and we used to talk
about like a you know ancient history
like 10 months ago we used to talk about
the problem of hallucination. Who here
has heard of the problem of AI
hallucination? So AI hallucination is
the tendency for AI because AI is really
doing a lot of like very very sort of
higher math um kind of prediction. Um
and it sometimes will give you a
prediction answer which is actually not
true because it's not really thinking
and it's not about truth and fiction.
It's about kind of prediction. So
sometimes the prediction will be wrong.
But AI is getting much better. And so
it's done the right thing ultimately
which is to tell you that it can't
figure out out from this data set.
Right? Um like you know a question I
would ask is what's the total number of
incursions by year. Right. Right. This
is the type of questions especially like
to me when I get a new data set these
first questions I ask I kind of call the
first date questions. You know I'm just
trying to get to know the data set and
kind of see what's in the different
columns and just like basic counts and
filters um are just a way to kind of
begin to see what's there.
And then exactly as that uh person in
the back said,
um you got to start making phone calls,
right? This is where the interviewer and
where the non- STEM, I guess you might
say, parts of the job kick in. You need
to go find an expert who knows a lot
about runway incursions. Maybe call
O'Hare and say, "Hey, I think you got
the most runway incursions last year.
What's up with that?" Right? Hey, hey,
Chat GBT, can you make that into a bar
chart?
So, uh, we chose a data set that we knew
we could download. Um, but there you can
do this with just about any data set
with mixed results. You got to be
careful. You should also kind of
probably check it to make sure that it's
right before you start calling and
accusing O'Hare airport of stuff. Uh,
but you can use this on almost any data
set. Uh, we tried before we got here
with some New York City data sets. It
works shockingly well. Um, and these are
great ways to get yourselves uh into
stories. So I think we have run out of
time.
Uh right.
So it makes me almost sad to see this
because it took me years of learning how
to write Python code to be able to take
a data set I had downloaded 30 seconds
before and begin to do these first day
questions and get to know it and start
to figure out what's there. And now
thanks to these tools, what we just were
farting around and did it in 10 minutes,
guys. It's just wild.
So go out, make good trouble, download
uh more troublesome data sets uh and uh
please thanks everybody.